Guide to the Archives of Irish America Material Culture Collection AIA.041
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish America Material Culture and Ephemera Collection
1915-2005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish America
AIA.041
10 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, 6 flat boxes, and 2 objects
The Archives of Irish America Material Culture collection is a conglomeration of objects individually donated or found in collections and removed.
Arrangement
Items are arranged alphabetically.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of a variety of items such as buttons, bumper stickers, hats, tickets, membership cards, pens, pins, and t-shirts -- many of them related to Irish organizations. Contents of the collection came in as individual accessions or as part of larger accessions, including the Dorothy Hayden Cudahy Irish Memories Collection, and were organized together into this artificial collection.
Historical Note
The Material Culture collection compliments the entire Archives of Irish America in that its contents provides information on many topics and individuals not formally represented in the other collections. The unique format of many of the materials - hats, t-shirts, bumper stickers - provide insight to scholars and researchers in the methods used to convey information within the Irish American community.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was created via active collection by staff, contributions from donors and from material removed from collections in the Archives. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1997.023, 2012.037, and 2019.114.
Custodial History
Items in the Material Culture collection were donated, purchased or found in other collections of the Archives.
Footballs (balls for sports).; Hats.; Memorabilia.; Cigar boxes.; Plaques (flat objects); T-shirts.; Bumper stickers.; Stationery.; Irish Americans.
- Armband: "Formation", undated; 300926 (Box 2, Object 6)
- Armbands: "Frank Stagg, RIP" (IRA hunger strike), c. 1970s; 300927 (Box 2, Object 5)
- Ashtray: "Ireland" / Made in the Republic of Ireland by N.B.C. Ltd., undated; 300922 (Box 4, Object 3)
- Badges, Name Tags, & Ribbons, 1945-1992; 320734 (Box 3, Object 4)
- Banner: Brehon Law Society, undated; 356245 (Box 8)
- Banner: Irish American Heritage Committee of the New York City Department of Education (Box 14)
- Baseball cap with image of Irish flag, undated; 300887 (Box 1, Object 5)
- Baseball cap with "N.Y. State Convention A.O.H. Niagra Falls 1987 Albany, N.Y. in '89" Silkscreen, 1989; 300888 (Box 1, Object 6)
- Bookmark: "An Olde Irish Toast", undated; 311766 (Box 2, Object 8)
- Bookmark with copper pence: Bank of Ireland, undated; 320748 (Box 3, Object 12)
- Bumper Sticker: "The Irish Will Remember in November", undated; 300928 (Box 2, Object 3)
  Memorabilia.; Hats.
- Bumper Sticker: "Save the Leprechaun", undated; 300912 (Box 3, Object 14)
- Bumper Sticker: "Strip Search the Queen", undated; 300920 (Box 3, Object 15)
- Bumper sticker: "There's every reason to buy Irish", undated; 300929 (Box 2, Object 3)
- Buttons and Pins, undated; 320735 (Box 3, Object 3)
- Calendar (magnet): Kathleen's of Donegal Irish Imports, 1998; 300924 (Box 3, Object 13)
- Calendar: shape of shamrock, undated; 300907 (Box 3, Object 6)
- Cigar Box: "Irish Molly O", undated; 300934 (Box 4, Object 2)
- Cigarette Card: Frank Riley, Irish American Athletic Club (member of 1908 American Olympic Team), undated; 356240
- Coasters (4): Harp, Guinness, Bank of Ireland, undated, 1998; 300921 (Box 2, Object 7)
- Concertina, undated (Box 12)
- Flags: U.S.A. and Republic of Ireland (small), undated; 300930 (Box 7)
- Game Passes, Polo Grounds: Gaelic Games, 1954-1958; 300917 (Box 3, Object 2)
- Handkerchief with embroidered green flower, undated; 356246 (Box 7)
- Hurling Ball, leather, undated; 300919 (Box 4, Object 1)
- Keychain: Irish Voice, 320714 (Box 3, Object 5)
- Lottery tickets: Irish Hospitals' Sweepstakes (John J. Cudahy), Oct 1985; 300925 (Box 3, Object 10)
- Moore Centenary Association of Newark, New Jersey, 1879-05-28 (Box Shared Tamiment 030, Folder 21)
- Mouse pad: Irish Echo, undated; 300899 (Box 1, Object 7)
- New York World's Fair Booklet, 1939 (Box Shared Tamiment 030, Folder 22)
- Paperweight: "Moynihan for Senate", undated; 300914 (Box 3, Object 7)
- Plaque: "An Old Irish Benediction", undated; 300884 (Box 1, Object 2)
- Plaque: County Clare P.B. & S. Association; to Michael Mahoney, undated; 311768 (Box 2, Object 11)
- Plaque: "Ireland Unfree Shall Never Be At Peace - 1916 - Patrick Pearse", undated; 311765 (Box 5, Object 3)
- Plaque: Irish American Cultural Institute, "The Irish Way Program", 1981; 320237 (Box 5, Object 2)
- Plaque: "Irish American Heritage Museum Charter Member", undated; 300883 (Box 2, Object 4)
- Photo on wood block: Dorothy Hayden Cudahy, undated; 300915 (Box 3, Object 1)
- Record Album: "The Irish Uprising, 1916-1922", undated; 311767 (Box 5, Object 1)
- Ribbon: Irish American Athletic Association Member: " Nothing too Good for the Irish-Americans" Banquet, 30 Oct 1911; 311764 (Box 2, Object 10)
- Rosary, undated; 300910 (Box 3, Object 5)
- Ruler: Bank of Ireland, undated; 300923 (Box 3, Object 11)
- Scally cap with "Hibernians/Budweiser" Patch, undated; 300885 (Box 1, Object 3)
- Stamp: Bank of Ireland, Deposits, undated; 300916 (Box 3, Object 8)
- Stamp: Doran Film Distribution: U.S. Distribution and Sales; wood and rubber, undated; 300913 (Box 3, Object 9)
- Stationery pad: Ladies Ancient Order of Hibernians, undated; 300886 (Box 1, Object 4)
- Stationery Sets (3): Aer Lingus 1st Class, undated; 300889 (Box 2, Object 1)
- Shoelaces with shamrocks, undated; 300918 (Box 2, Object 9)
- T-Shirt: 22nd Annual Washington Irish Folk Festival, Montgomery County Fairgrounds [MD}, Sep 5 1998-Sep 6 1998; 356241 (Box 6, Object 10)
- T-Shirt: "Conradh na Gailge – Craobh Baile Phit", undated; 300904 (Box 6, Object 1)
- T-Shirt: Coogan Salsa Blues and Shamrocks, NYC "Remember Captain Frederick Ill, FDNY, Mar 2, 2003; 356242 (Box 6, Object 11)
- T-Shirt: "Free Jim Barr – Irish Political Prisoner in America", undated; 300901 (Box 6, Object 2)
- T-Shirt: "The Great Hunger", undated; 300931 (Box 6, Object 3)
- T-Shirt: Ireland Worldcup 1994, 300933 (Box 6, Object 4)
- T-Shirt: "Irish Emigrant Vote Campaign, ©IEVC '91", 1991; 300902 (Box 6, Object 5)
- T-Shirt: "Republic of Ireland, World Cup '94", 1994; 300905 (Box 6, Object 6)
- T-Shirt: "Riverdance", 1995-2000 (Box 15)
- T-Shirt: "Scannān '92: A Festival of Modern Irish Film", 1992; 300903 (Box 6, Object 7)
- T-Shirt: "Support Irish Political Prisoners • H-Block and Armagh Comm.", undated; 300900 (Box 6, Object 8)
- T-Shirt: "Ulysses S. Grant and the Irish" - Wildgeese.com, undated; 300932 (Box 6, Object 9)
- Tea Towel: "County Roscomman" (linen), 356244 (Box 7)
- Tea Towel: "Famous Irish Americans" (linen/cotton), 356243 (Box 7)